Guide to the Correspondence, Albert L. Guérard and Albert Thierry
Department of Special Collections
Correspondence, Albert L. Guérard and Albert Thierry,
Unit date
Special Collections M0899
Guérard, Albert Leon, 1880-1959.
0.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Biography
Frenchmen Albert Léon Guérard (1880-1959) and Albert Thierry (1881-1915) were friends from childhood whose correspondence reflects their shared interests in French and Anglo-American literature and writing. Guérard came to the United States in 1906 to teach at Williams College. He taught at Stanford University from 1907-1946 when he retired, except for 12 years between 1913-1925 when he was at Rice University and served in the war. He was the author of numerous books on French history and intellectual life. Thierry was a Proudhonian socialist, anarchist, and schoolteacher who wrote poetry as well as several longer works of fiction and theory. At the same time, he also served as a soldier in the French army from around 1902 until he was killed in 1915.
Scope and Content
The Albert L. Guérard and Albert Thierry Correspondence Collection consists of 1 manuscript box. Other collections of ALG papers can be found in the Stanford Special Collections, the Hoover Institution Archives, and at the University of Pennsylvania. This collection is composed of four types of materials, all pertaining directly to Thierry and arranged as follows. The letters written by Albert Thierry to Albert L. Guérard from 1902 to 1915, when Thierry was killed in the First World War are arranged in chronological order. Most letters are written in French, but the correspondence from 1905-1907, when Thierry was stationed in Germany and Austria, is in German. Subjects discussed in these letters include English and French literature, Guérard's and Thierry's writings, Thierry's life as a soldier and a teacher, and the war. The second group of materials is 6 handwritten sheets written or copied by Thierry, primarily copies of poems by Emile Verhaeren. The third section contains 2 letters from 1957-58, the correspondence between ALG and Roger Petitjean. These discuss AT's works and ALG's views on current events in France. Finally, the collection also contains a biographical work about AT and a copy of his novel, entitled Le Sourire Blessé.
Access Terms
Thierry, Albert, 1881-1915.; Thierry, Albert, 1881-1915. Le Sourire Blesse.; Authors, French.; French literature--20th century.; World War, 1914-1918--France.; France--History--20th century.; French Prophets of Yesterday.; French Civilization in the Nineteenth Century.
Container List
- 5 letters. Subjects: English and French literature, AT is soldier in the 106e, Châlons-sur-Marne., 1902 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 13 letters. 1903 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- 5 letters and 4 postcards. 1904 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- 10 letters in German. AT is stationed in Weimar. 1905 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 12 letters in German. AT is stationed in Vienna. 1906-7 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 7 letters. 1908-9 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- 4 letters. 1910-11 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- 2 letters. Subjects: International language. 1912 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- 2 letters. Subjects: On ALG's book French Prophets. 1913 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- 5 letters. Subjects: Thierry on his work, on ALG's French Civilization, race, the war. 1914 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- 3 postcards. Subjects: the war, notes from the battlefield, ALG as "American citizen, yet son of France" and his non-involvement in war. 1915 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- 6 handwritten sheets of writings: n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - - Notes on "La Triomphe de la Vie," a poem by Rousseau.
  - - "Les lois d'imitation," by AT?
  - - "Qu'est-ce que l'art?" by L. Tolstoy, French transl. T. deWysyewa.
  - - "Le Bazar," by Emile Verhaeren, Belgian writer. (Les Villes Tentaculaires), Reine Blanche. June 1894
  - - "Les Villes" and "Les Usines" by Emile Verhaeren. (Les Villes Tentaculaires), Ere Nouvelle. July 1894
  - - "Les Spectacles," by Emile Verhaeren. (Les Villes Tentaculaires), Mercure de France. July 1895
- 2 letters: (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Subjects: Edition of AT's works or book about AT using ALG's letters; ALG's views on France and UN, United Europe, Union Française, French Communism; Algerian question.
  - - From ALG to Roger Petitjean. 17 Dec. 1957
  - - From Roger Petitjean to ALG. 5 Jan. 1958
- "Albert Thierry (Etudes et Opinions)," publication of Les Primeurs, revue d'étude et d'art. n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Subjects: biographical essays, Thierry's works (primarily poetry), and bibliography.
- Albert Thierry, Le Sourire Blessé. Paris: Editions de la Nouvelle Revue Française, 1922. 8th ed. 1922 (Box 1, Folder 15)